<section anchor="ErrorCodes" title="Error Codes">
    <t>
        Error codes are 32-bit fields that are used in
        <x:ref>RST_STREAM</x:ref>
        and
        <x:ref>GOAWAY</x:ref>
        frames to convey the reasons for the stream or connection error.
    </t>

    <t>
        Error codes share a common code space. Some error codes apply only to either streams or the
        entire connection and have no defined semantics in the other context.
    </t>

    <t>
        The following error codes are defined:
        <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="NO_ERROR (0x0):" anchor="NO_ERROR">
                The associated condition is not a result of an error. For example, a
                <x:ref>GOAWAY</x:ref>
                might include this code to indicate graceful shutdown of a
                connection.
            </t>
            <t hangText="PROTOCOL_ERROR (0x1):" anchor="PROTOCOL_ERROR">
                The endpoint detected an unspecific protocol error. This error is for use when a more
                specific error code is not available.
            </t>
            <t hangText="INTERNAL_ERROR (0x2):" anchor="INTERNAL_ERROR">
                The endpoint encountered an unexpected internal error.
            </t>
            <t hangText="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR (0x3):" anchor="FLOW_CONTROL_ERROR">
                The endpoint detected that its peer violated the flow-control protocol.
            </t>
            <t hangText="SETTINGS_TIMEOUT (0x4):" anchor="SETTINGS_TIMEOUT">
                The endpoint sent a
                <x:ref>SETTINGS</x:ref>
                frame but did not receive a response in a
                timely manner. See
                <xref target="SettingsSync"/>
                ("Settings Synchronization").
            </t>
            <t hangText="STREAM_CLOSED (0x5):" anchor="STREAM_CLOSED">
                The endpoint received a frame after a stream was half-closed.
            </t>
            <t hangText="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR (0x6):" anchor="FRAME_SIZE_ERROR">
                The endpoint received a frame with an invalid size.
            </t>
            <t hangText="REFUSED_STREAM (0x7):" anchor="REFUSED_STREAM">
                The endpoint refused the stream prior to performing any application processing (see
                <xref target="Reliability"/>
                for details).
            </t>
            <t hangText="CANCEL (0x8):" anchor="CANCEL">
                Used by the endpoint to indicate that the stream is no longer needed.
            </t>
            <t hangText="COMPRESSION_ERROR (0x9):" anchor="COMPRESSION_ERROR">
                The endpoint is unable to maintain the header compression context for the connection.
            </t>
            <t hangText="CONNECT_ERROR (0xa):" anchor="CONNECT_ERROR">
                The connection established in response to a
                <xref target="CONNECT">CONNECT
                    request
                </xref>
                was reset or abnormally closed.
            </t>
            <t hangText="ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM (0xb):" anchor="ENHANCE_YOUR_CALM">
                The endpoint detected that its peer is exhibiting a behavior that might be generating
                excessive load.
            </t>
            <t hangText="INADEQUATE_SECURITY (0xc):" anchor="INADEQUATE_SECURITY">
                The underlying transport has properties that do not meet minimum security
                requirements (see<xref target="TLSUsage"/>).
            </t>
            <t hangText="HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED (0xd):" anchor="HTTP_1_1_REQUIRED">
                The endpoint requires that HTTP/1.1 be used instead of HTTP/2.
            </t>
        </list>
    </t>
    <t>
        Unknown or unsupported error codes MUST NOT trigger any special behavior. These MAY be
        treated by an implementation as being equivalent to<x:ref>INTERNAL_ERROR</x:ref>.
    </t>
</section>